Mary Chrystie Papers, 1833-1841: Finding Aid
Cotsen Children's Library
- Correspondence, 1833-1841; 1830s-1840s; 15.0 folders (Box 1)
  - Post-mortem Items, 1843; 7.0 items
    - To Unknown, Undated; 4.0 pages 19.3 x 24.5 cm One sheet folded in half, with a black border. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      No date; from Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt, to "Sir," perhaps Reverend F.P. Tappan. A short note which accompanied a variety of biographical materials about Mary Chrystie: "I send the materials for the biographical sketch in which you have so kindly interested yourself"; it is not clear exactly which materials this note did accompany; Mary Few says only "I have sent her journal &c thinking that you might find it interesting to trace the development of her character and sentiments."
    - A Hagiography of Mary Chrystie, Undated; 12.0 pages Sheet 1, 25.4 x 42 cm, with a 6.2 x 21 cm piece of paper sewn onto the bottom of the second leaf; sheet 2, 25.4 x 42 cm; sheet 3, 25.2 x 39.6 cm. 3 sheets folded in half to create 12 pages; each sheet is loose, although two sheets show signs of having been bound at some point. Sheet 1 has 4 pages of writing; Sheet 2, 1 page of writing; Sheet 3, 4 pages of writing. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      No date; at least partially written by Albert Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's father, and perhaps by her mother Frances Few Chrystie. A hagiography of Mary Chrystie. 9 written pages describing in some detail Mary Chrystie's spiritual devotion, character, qualities, and latent intelligence, as well as her loving relationship with her family--especially her extremely close relationship with her mother, who was described by Mary as being her "oldest sister. You never command me, but you tell me what is best, and you deny me nothing, without convincing me it is best I should do without it"; Mary is descibed as having begun walking "at less than 10 months old"; at 19 months she was freely talking; at 3 years of age she "could repeat in her own language the substance" of Watt's First Catechism for Children; at age 4 she read very well; and "Religious truth made a sensible impression," so much so that she prayed to be forgiven "for every sin that she thought she had been committing"; she did not associate much with friends or servants, choosing instead to invest her time in her immediate family; she was a "conspicuous" participant in her father's Sunday evening family Bible class (which the domestics were also invited to attend); while traveling to Italy Mary told her mother, "I was never so happy in religion as I am now--I never loved to pray so much," a statement that her mother interpreted as a fortelling of Mary's death; her loving character is testified to: "The last night of her life while resting her head on her Father's bosom she said Father you promised me a watch when we got to Geneva. Give it to Mother--do not forget"; very interestingly, it is mentioned that when Mary was aged 5 or 6 "a daily journal was begun to be kept of her misdeeds which was read to her at night. Nothing pained her more than this journal, she would often entreat that it might not be read & sometimes refuse to listen--but the effect was always salutary. The journal was not always kept, but if any fault seemed to be gaining strength the journal would be renewed for a week or month or longer. Some pages of it have been found and will show her early character better than any thing else (see above, item 9 of the "Prayers, Poems, and Miscellaneous Notes" series for an example). Further anecdotes detailing Mary's gentle and loving character can be found throughout these pages.
    - Note by Frances Few Chrystie, 1843 November 24; 2.0 pages 12.4 x 19.3 cm One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      November 24, 1843; A note by Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, describing her grief at the death of her daughter the previous Spring in Nice, her own apparent experience with the "invisible world" and ministering angels in the aftermath of Mary's death, and a dream she had on May 28th, in Bologna, in which she was visited by her aunt Lizzy who told her, in response to Mrs. Chrystie's query as to whether or not Lizzy had seen Mary, "All is well" (See the "Miscellaneous Letters" series, item 9, for another description of this dream). Mrs. Chrystie concludes: "I note these things that I may keep in remembrance the goodness of the Lord to a suffering creature so comforted & so sustained. With dark events I strove/ And found when rightly understood/ All messages of love."
    - Note by Frances Few Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 19.7 x 25.2 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      No date; A note by Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, setting the record straight about Mary's honesty: "in mentioning her propensity to not speak the truth, I fear I may be misunderstood, it showed itself only when she was a very little child..."; by the time Mary was 7 or 8 "so strict was her veracity & so entirely to be depended upon" that Mary told the truth even to her own detriment; also described is Mary's tolerant and forgiving nature; mention is made of the Chrystie family's trip to Europe, and it seems that it was in large part motivated by medical advice: "[Mary's] physicians said that she ought not to return to America in two years"; Mary, however, wanted to return home sooner rather than later in order to prevent her mother from feeling herself "an exile" and so she might grow up close to her friends so as not to differ from them or lose any of their love.
    - To Reverend W. Tappan, Undated; 4.0 pages 19.8 x 25.2 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      No date; from Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, to Reverend W. Tappan. A note with editorial corrections and suggestions made by Mrs. Chrystie in regard to a memoir the Reverend Tappan is writing about Mary; Mrs. Chrystie has made a couple of specific changes: changing "Mother" to "parents" and effacing the word "tyrannical" from the third page; she also urges the Reverend to place more emphasis on the love between Mary and her father and brother--if her brother William is not mentioned frequently in her journals, it is because she only began keeping a diary after Willie had left for school; Mrs. Chrystie supports the writing of this "memoir" so "that the simple Christian experience of my blessed child will lead some 'little ones' to Jesus that dear Saviour on whom she [Mary] reposed in life and in death."
    - To Reverend W. Tappan, Undated; 4.0 pages 22.6 x 36.9 cm One sheet folded in half with watermark. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      No date; From Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt, to Reverend W. Tappan. A note describing Mary Chrystie's intellectual qualities in order to help Reverend Tappan form "a just estimate of the dear child in whom you have so kindly interested youself"; Mary's great facility with geometry is described, as is her extreme enjoyment of reading and writing--her enthusiam for recording her thoughts and desires "induced a habit of careless writing & careless spelling which made her fall below the boarding-school standard--but it had also given her a peculiar facility in expressing herself, while her love of reading had furnished her with ideas which made her superior to her companions in composition."
    - To Frances Few Chrystie, 1843 July 8; 4.0 pages 20.2 x 25.5 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      July 8, 1843, Savannah, Georgia; from Mary T/F(?) to Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. Transcription of a poem entitled "Epitaph on a Young Lady Aged Eighteen" by Miss H. More; with a note: "Copied for F. Chrystie by her friend Mary T/F(?). The Poem is "Epitaph on Miss Gwatkin" by Hannah More (1745-1833).
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1802-1907; 14.0 items
    Letters and notes, most written at the end of the 19th and beginning of the 20th century. Mostly by Chrystie family members and their descendants. The letters cover these topics of interest: Marion Letcher's research on the Few family, Mary Chrystie's death, the Civil War, death of Colonel William Few, and sketches by Mary Chrystie.
    - Receipt for Silver, 1871 May 31; 1.0 pages 16 x 22.5 cm 1 incomplete letterhead page. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      May 31, 1871, New York; part of a receipt for silver bought by William Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's brother, from Starr & Marcus of No. 22 John Street, Up Stairs, New York, New York; purchased items include 1 sterling silver tea service, 5 pieces ($385); 2 dozen sterling silver table spoons ($115.50); 2 dozen sterling silver table forks ($109); 1 1/2 dozen sterling silver dessert spoons ($56.87); 1 dozen sterling silver dessert forks ($37.87); 2 dozen sterling silver tea spoons ($54); 1 sterling silver soup ladle ($25); 1 dozen sterling silver egg spoons ($25); 1 gorham plated tureen ($60); 1 gorham plated kettle & stand ($41.50); total cost of these items: $909.74; the rest of the receipt is lost.
    - To Mrs. William Chrystie, 1904 November 19; 4.0 pages 16.5 x 26.2 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      November 19, 1904, Washington, D.C.; from Marion Letcher to Mrs. William Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's brother's wife(?), residing at Hastings on the Hudson, New York; Marion Letcher (possibly the Marion Letcher who was United States consul in Chihuahua during the Mexican revolution) requests the help of Mr. William Chrystie in his/her attempt to compile information for a biography of Colonel William Few, Mary Chrystie's grandfather. Marion Letcher specififes a letter written by Dr. Ignatius Few to Miss Mary Few in 1837 that is included in Mrs. William Chrystie's collection. Also see item 9 of this series, below.
    - To Frances Few Chrystie, 1880 July 5; 4.0 pages 20.4 x 25.4 cm One ruled sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      July 5, 1880, Princeton, NJ; from a Ms. "Chgimi"(?) to Mrs. F. F. Chrystie, presumably Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. A 2 page letter thanking Mrs. Chrystie for her hospitality during a recent visit.
    - To Frances Few Chrystie, 1878 August 18; 4.0 pages 19.7 x 24.2 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      August 18, 1878, Quebec; from Emily (William Few Chrystie's daughter?) to her grandmother Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. Emily describes her trip to Quebec, what she has seen, and where she has gone.
    - To Mary Few, Undated; 4.0 pages 25.3 x 40.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Dated "Saturday Night 18th" (no year, but possibly 1842, the year of Mary Chrystie's death); postmarked November 23 or 29 at Rhinebeck, NY; from Mr. Gallatin to Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt; a brief note lamenting Mary Chrystie's death, along with a 22-line eulogistic poem written by Mary Gallatin in honor of Mary Chrystie. The poem urges faith in the face of grief, beginning: "In foreign lands her sacred dust is laid/ By stranger lips her funeral rites were said,/ Youth, Beauty, genius, fortune's favours given/ Unheeded all, her eye was fixt on heaven..."
    - To Frances Few Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 20.5 x 33.1 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      No date; from Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt, to Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. Mary Few relays news of various mutual acquaintances and family friends, mentions a letter she has received from Willie Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's brother, in which he mentions his father's ill health, and anticipates Frances's visit to "the south" (Georgia?).
    - To Mary Few, Undated; 4.0 pages 25.5 x 40.3 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Dated August 14 (no year, but after Mary Chrystie's death in 1842), written at Hell Gate; from T. F. Desmond(?) to Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt; a 40-line poem commemorating Mary Chrystie's death; at the top of the first page is a note in pencil written in a different hand: "Lines by Mrs. D." The poem compares Mary Chrystie's short life to that of a rose: "But its quiet and star like beauty told/ Too plainly on earth 'twas not meant to unfold." Now she rests "in the sunlight of God's own eye;/ Where the leaf never droops and the flowers never die."
    - To Maria Nicholson, 1802 October 1; 4.0 pages 24.8 x 40 cm One sheet folded in half, watermark of a crown and horn (and more). Remains of a red wax seal. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      October 1 1802, New York; from James Nicholson (Mary's maternal great-grandfather and the father of Catherine Nicholson Few) to his daughter Maria (perhaps Mary's great aunt Maria Montgomery, see above "Miscellaneous Letters" series, item 6). A brief letter in which Mr. Nicholson informs his daughter of his improving health.
    - To Unknown, 1907 July 5; 8.0 pages 20.3 x 25.2 cm Two sheets folded in half, University Club Washington letterhead. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      July 5, 1907 (dated at end of letter), University Club Washington letterhead; from Marion Letcher (possibly the Marion Letcher who was United States consul in Chihuahua during the Mexican revolution) to his/her cousin. A letter discussing the genealogical project about the Few family that Letcher is undertaking (See item 2 of this series, from the same correspondent).
    - To Emily, undated; 4.0 pages 20.3 x 26.6 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Dated "Saturday 30th(?) January" (no year, but written during the Civil War; possibly in 1864 when January 30 fell on a Saturday, if the date is correct); from an aunt in Georgia(?) to Emily, possibly the daughter of William Few Chrystie (Mary Chrystie's brother). Recalls mutual acquaintances; mentions that "Mr. Chrystie had been very sick"; a little over 4 lines of writing at the bottom of the first page are nearly completely crossed out; at the top of page 2 the author expresses concern over a man whom the family has "not hear a word from," stating "I have no doubt he was killed." Later on p. 2 reference is made to one Frank Cocke(?), a member of the signal corps who was killed in Savannah; "There is much sorrow in the land and many of the most loved have been call (sic) away, and yet would you believe the people are mainly gay..."; p. 4 lists other acquaintances who have died, such as the minister's wife, as well as a Mr. Henry who "has lost his mind"; closes with "My dear child I shall make every effort to go North if my life is spared, if I cannot obtain a Passport, I will try by the way of Memphis or Nashville."
    - Lecture Notes, 1859 March 8; 4.0 pages 21 x 33.3 cm One page folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Lecture notes in an unknown hand, in pencil with some pen; "Notes on Real Property--Professor Washburne"; "Criminal Law"; the names "Thomas" and "Singleton" appear frequently, as does the date 1776 (at the top left of the first page and all across the top of the second page); on the final page is a doodle of a square-rigger at full sail.
    - To Catherine Few, 1828 August 14; 4.0 pages 24.6 x 40 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      August 14, 1828, Steamboat North America; from Mr. Stewart to Mrs. Few (Catherine Few, Mary Chrystie's grandmother); Stewart writes to Catherine Few to offer his condolences on the death of her husband, Colonel William Few (1748-1828).
    - Sketches by Mary Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 28.2 x 43.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Undated pencil sketches by Mary Chrystie (with Mary's initials): tree boughs and foliage, a church, a fence post and flower, and a footbridge.
    - Sketches by Mary Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 28 x 43.3 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Undated sketches by Mary Chrystie; 4 sketches of houses (timberframe, thatched roof, and stone cottage) in pencil, with pencil sketch of flowers (partially colored with green and brown watercolors); on verso is a sketch of a young boy wearing a hat and holding a kite.
- Storybooks and Journals, 1831-1837; 7.0 items
  Mary Chrystie's childhood journals, and stories of her own composition, mostly about children. Some notebooks undated; some are dated between 1836 and 1837. There is also a packet of writings by Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, about her young daughter. Mary's journals cover these topics of interest: Bible verses and morality; Mary's education; children and families; Mary's grief over the death of a nest of birds.
  - Notebook, Undated; 16.0 pages 10.1 x 16.3 cm Small notebook with unlined paper and grey card wrappers. 16 pages. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    16 pages, all with inscription, unpaged. Mary Chrystie's signature on inside front wrapper; and written on inside front wrapper in her mother, Frances Few Chrystie's hand: "Written at 7 years of age". Notebook contains a story entitled "Little Tom and his Mother"; 2 hymns ("Hark! the skies with music sound..." and "begone, unbelief, my Saviour is near..."); a short story (really Bible quotations) about two children who memorize Matthew 5:3-7; text of the Golden Rule; an unfinished story of the discovery of an abandoned baby (continues after skipping 2 pages); an assortment of moral verses; pencil drawing of a country house and a neighboring church; beginning of a poem called "Robin"; beginning of the Guy Fawkes day poem "5th of November".
  - Notebook, 1836 March 8; 38.0 pages 19.5 x 16.5 cm Brown marbled paper wrappers, lined paper. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    38 pages; 14 pages with inscriptions at front of book, unpaged. On inside front wrapper: Mary's signature, date of March 8, Princeton 1836; "Continuation of Ellinor Randolph" (a short story Mary was writing); "Written at eleven years of age" (in pencil in her mother Frances Few Chrystie's hand). Blue paper label with script "Children's Tales" pasted on front wrappers. Notebook contains continuation of a story entitled "Ellinor Randolph" that Mary began writing in another book; a story entitled "The Tyrannical Girl" (on detached pages); a story entitled "Louisa & Harriet". A page of writing near the middle of the notebook has been torn out and is missing.
  - Notebook, 1836 March 14; 40.0 pages 16.8 x 19.5 cm Brown marbled paper wrappers, lined paper. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    40 pages, 28 of them with inscriptions, unpaged. On inside front wrapper: Mary Chrystie's signature, dated Princeton 1836 March 14. "The Washington Family...1"; "Alfred Templeton...7"; "Written at the age of ten (written over struck word "eight") years" (in pen in mother Frances Few Chrystie's hand). Blue paper label with script "Children's Tales by Mary Chrystie" pasted on front wrapper. Written on vertical edge of inside rear wrapper: "Do dear Willie won't you" in Mary's hand. Contains the short stories "The Washington Family"; "Alfred Templeton"; and an untitled short story starring "Old Mr. Ausburn".
  - Notebook, Undated; 44.0 pages 15.6 x 18.7 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    40 pages with an additional 4 pages sewn in at the rear of the booklet. White paper wrappers printed in black (pictured on the front is a mail coach drawn by four horses with 4 lines of verse beneath it); on outside rear wrapper are printed addition and multiplication tables and an illustration of a fire engine and firemen. Notebook printed by R. Lockwood's School Book Depository, No. 415 Broadway,--First door below Canal-street--New York. Main text block is detached. At least one folio has been torn from the notebook.
    44 pages, all with inscriptions. Laurel-framed box at the top of the wrapper enclosing: "Property of Mary Chrystie". Written on inside of front wrapper is a long addition problem, various squiggles, the word "spanled" (?), and a small drawing of a house and tree. White paper wrappers printed in black (pictured on the front is a mail coach drawn by four horses with 4 lines of verse beneath it); on outside rear wrapper are printed addition and multiplication tables and an illustration of a fire engine and firemen. Notebook includes short stories entitled "Albertina and Mary"; a "true story" entitled "The stolen child..." a hymn ("Oh. Lord thou good and great / To thee my praise I'll bring..."; authorship is claimed by Mary herself); and poem entitled "My Father at the Helm". 2 folios sewn in at the end of the text include a short story written by Mary at a much earlier age; a pencil drawing of a country house; the beginning of a story entitled "Harriate and Ann"; and an incomplete short piece signed by Mary's brother, William Few Chrystie. At least one folio has been torn from the notebook.
  - Notebook, 1837; 58.0 pages 16.6. x 20.2 cm Brown paper wrappers printed in black (pictured on front is an engraving of a man lost at sea holding on to a hot air balloon); white paper label with yellow markings and the word "Journal" written on it pasted beneath the engraving, and presumably covering printer/publisher information; multiplication table printed on outside of rear wrapper; 12 additional pages sewn in at the front of the notebook. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    58 pages, all with inscriptions. Brown paper wrappers printed in black (pictured on front is an engraving of a man lost at sea holding on to a hot air balloon); white paper label with yellow markings and the word "Journal" written on it pasted beneath the engraving, and presumably covering printer/publisher information; multiplication table printed on outside of rear wrapper; 12 additional pages sewn in at the front of the notebook. On inside front wrapper is a small profile of a man's head, and written in pen in the hand of Mary Chrystie's mother, Frances Few Chrystie: "Mary Chrystie 12 years old"; inside of rear wrapper covered with small drawings and doodles and the words "William Few Chrystie has this book or in French dis livre" written in the hand of Mary's brother, William Few Chrystie. First 4 sewn in pages: letter from Mary Chrystie in Saratoga Springs to her brother, Willy, in New York City; final 8 sewn in pages: journal entries beginning July 12, 1837 (written while in Saratoga Springs) in which Mary describes family activities in Saratoga. Included in the sewn in pages is an entry from July 16, 1837 describing the death of a family of birds that nested outside their house, and including a 24-line poem written by Mary's mother, Frances Few Chrystie, to commemorate the birds. The notebook's main text block includes journal entries from July 23, 1837 to December 24, 1837. Journal entries include descriptions of daily activities, Bible texts, and other lessons. Mary's mother, Frances Few Chrystie, has corrected many of Mary's errors and commented on her mistakes, penmanship, and overall writing style. It is clear that Mary's journals were evaluated on a regular basis by her mother (see other letters and journal entries).
  - Notebook, Undated; 48.0 pages 16 x 19.2 cm Marbled brown and black stiff paper wrappers; pasted on inside front wrapper is bookseller's sticker: B. G. Jansen, / Bookseller, Stationer, and / Law Blank Seller, / 158 Nassau-st., N. Y.". (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Marbled brown and black stiff paper wrappers; pasted on inside front wrapper is bookseller's sticker: B. G. Jansen, / Bookseller, Stationer, and / Law Blank Seller, / 158 Nassau-st., N. Y.". Written in pencil on inside of front wrapper is "Mary Albertine" Mary Chrystie's first and middle name, and an outline of the subjects Mary covered in her Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday lessons: Monday: Bible lesson, Phrases, Exercise, verb, Composition Tuesday: Geography, Theme, History, Dictation, Grammer (sic), Exposition(?) Wednesday: G_____(sic), Translation, Exercise Notebook includes various lessons, such as compositions ("Life of a canary bird"; "A Shipwreck"; "Life of Oliver Cromwell"; "Life of a sailor left on desert land"; "An account of the destruction of tea in Boston harbour"; a biography of the biblical figure Ruth; a description of events from the Revolutionary War; "A holy day"; "Descriptions of Mr. Bolton's house at New Rochelle"; a description of Norway; and 3 sample letters.